Let's say you're trying to lose 20 pounds,
or boost your immunity,
or increase your ability to fight COVID,
or even cancer.
Well, the amazing thing is,
with the right diet,
you're well on your way to
achieving these vital health goals.
Welcome to the Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I'm your host, Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at
how losing weight
without rearranging your
gastrointestinal anatomy
carries advantages beyond
just the lack of surgical risk.
The surgical community objects
to the characterization
of bariatric surgery as
merely internal jaw wiring,
cutting into healthy organs just
to discipline people’s behavior.
They’ve gone as far as to
rename it “metabolic surgery,”
suggesting the anatomical
rearrangements cause changes
in digestive hormones that
offer unique physiological benefits.
As evidence, they
point to the remarkable
remission rates for type 2 diabetes.
After bariatric surgery,
about 50% of obese diabetics
and 75% of super-obese
diabetics go into remission,
meaning they have
normal blood sugars
on a regular diet off
all diabetes medications.
The normalization in
blood sugars can happen
within literally days after the surgery.
And then fifteen years after
the surgery, 30% may remain free
from their diabetes
(compared to a 7% cure rate
in a nonsurgical control group).
Are we sure it was the surgery, though?
One of the most challenging
parts of bariatric surgery
is lifting the liver.
Since obese individuals tend
to have such large fatty livers,
this can be tricky, risking
liver injury and bleeding.
Enlarged livers are one of the
most common reasons less invasive
laparoscopic surgery turns into
to fully invasive open surgery,
leaving the patient with a large
full-belly scar, and increased
risk of wound infections,
complications, and recovery time.
But lose even just 5%
of your body weight
and your fatty liver may shrink by 10%.
That’s why those awaiting bariatric
surgery are put on a diet.
Then after surgery,
patients are typically placed
on an extremely low-calorie
liquid diet for weeks.
Could their improvement
in blood sugars just be
from the calorie restriction,
rather than some sort of
surgical metabolic magic?
Researchers decided to put it to the test.
At a bariatric surgery clinic
at the University of Texas,
patients with type 2 diabetes
scheduled for gastric bypass
volunteered to first
undergo an identical period
of calorie restriction
but without the surgery.
They were placed in the hospital
and put on the same diet
they would be on immediately before
and after the surgery for ten days,
averaging less than 500 calories a
day to mimic the surgical situation.
Then, the researchers waited
a few months so the patients
would gain the weight back and,
then put them through the actual
surgery matched day-to-day
to the diets they were on before.
So, the same patients, same diets,
just with or without the actual surgery.
If there was some sort
of metabolic benefit
to the anatomical rearrangement,
they would have done better
after the actual surgery, but in
some ways they actually did worse.
The calorie restriction alone
resulted in similar improvements
in blood sugar, pancreatic
function, and insulin sensitivity,
but several measures of
diabetic control improved
significantly more without the surgery.
So, the surgery seemed to put
them at a metabolic disadvantage.
The calorie restriction works by
first mobilizing fat out of the liver.
Type 2 diabetes is thought
to be caused by fat building up
in the liver and then spilling
over into the pancreas.
Everyone may have a
“personal fat threshold”
for the safe storage of excess fat.
When that limit is exceeded,
fat gets deposited in the liver,
where it causes insulin resistance.
The liver attempts to offload some
of the fat (in the form of a fat
transport molecule called VLDL),
which then gets stuck in the pancreas
and can kill off the
cells that produce insulin.
By the time diabetes
is diagnosed, half of our
insulin-producing cells
may have been destroyed.
Put people on a low-calorie diet, though,
and this entire process can be reversed.
A large enough negative
calorie balance can cause
a profound drop in liver
fat, sufficient to resurrect
liver insulin sensitivity
within seven days.
Keep it up, and the liver stops
spitting out fat enough to help
normalize pancreatic fat levels
and function within just eight weeks.
Once you drop below your
personal fat threshold,
you should then be able
to resume normal intake
and still keep your diabetes at bay.
The bottom line is that
type 2 diabetes is reversible
with weight loss, if you
catch it early enough.
Lose more than 30 pounds and
nearly 90% of those who have had
type 2 diabetes for less than
four years can achieve remission,
whereas it may only be reversible
in 50% of whose who’ve lived
with the disease for
longer than eight years.
That’s losing weight
with diet alone, though.
The remission numbers for
diabetics losing even more
than twice as much weight
with bariatric surgery
may only be around 75% up
to 8 years and 40% after that.
Losing weight without
resorting to surgery
may offer other benefits as well.
Diabetics losing weight with diet
alone can significantly improve
markers of systemic inflammation,
such as tumor necrosis factor,
whereas levels significantly
worsened when about
the same amount of weight was
lost from a gastric bypass.
What about diabetic complications?
One of the reasons we don’t want
diabetes is that we don’t want
to go blind, and we don’t
want to have to go on dialysis.
Reversing diabetes with
bariatric surgery can improve
kidney function, but
surprisingly, it may not prevent
the appearance or progression
of diabetic vision loss.
Perhaps because bariatric
surgery affects diet quantity
but not necessarily diet quality.
This reminds me of a famous
study published in the
New England Journal of Medicine
that randomized thousands
of diabetics to an
intensive lifestyle program
that focused on weight loss.
Ten years in, the study was
stopped prematurely because
the diabetics weren’t living any longer
or having any fewer heart attacks.
This may be because
they remained on the same
heart-clogging diet but
just in smaller portions.
In our next story, we look
at how weight regain
after bariatric surgery can have
devastating psychological effects.
How sustainable is the weight
loss from bariatric surgery?
Most gastric bypass patients end
up regaining some of the
fat they lose over the first
year or two after surgery,
but five years later three-quarters
maintain at least a 20% weight loss.
The typical trajectory for someone
who starts out obese at 285 pounds,
for example, would be to drop
to an overweight 178 pounds
two years after bariatric
surgery but then regain
back up to an obese 207 pounds.
This has been chalked up
to “grazing” behavior,
where compulsive eaters
may shift from binging,
which becomes more difficult
post-surgery, to eating
smaller amounts constantly
throughout the day.
Eight years out, about half
of gastric bypass patients
continue to describe
episodes of disordered eating.
As one pediatric obesity
specialist described,
“I have seen many patients who put
chocolate bars into a blender
with some cream, just
to pass technically
installed obstacles
[like a gastric band].”
Bariatric surgery advertising
is filled with happily-ever-after
fairytale narratives of cherry-
picked outcomes offering,
as one ad analysis put it, “the full
Cinderella-romance happy ending.”
This may contribute to the finding
that patients often overestimate
the amount of weight they’ll
lose with the procedure and
underestimate the difficulty
of the recovery process.
Surgery forces profound changes
in eating habits requiring slow,
thoroughly chewed, small bites.
Your stomach goes from the
volume of two softballs
to down to the size of half a
tennis ball in stomach stapling,
and half of a ping-pong ball in
the case of gastric bypass or banding.
As you can imagine, weight
regain after surgery can have
devastating psychological
effects, as patients may feel
they failed their last resort.
This may explain why
bariatric surgery patients
are at a high risk of
depression and suicide.
Now severe obesity alone may
increase risk of suicidal depression,
but even at the same weight,
those going through surgery
appear to be at higher risk.
At the same BMI, age, and
gender, bariatric surgery
recipients have nearly four
times the odds of suicide
compared with counterparts
not undergoing the procedure.
Most convincingly, before-and-after
mirror-image analyses
show the risk of serious self-harm
increases post-surgery
among the same individuals.
About 1 in 50 bariatric surgery
patients end up killing themselves
or being hospitalized for
self-harm or attempted suicide.
And this only includes confirmed
suicides, excluding masked attempts
such as overdoses of
“undetermined intention.”
Bariatric surgery patients
also have an elevated risk
of accidental death,
though some of this may be
due to changes in alcohol metabolism.
Give gastric bypass
folks two shots of vodka,
and because of their altered
anatomy their blood alcohol level
shoots past the legal driving
limit within minutes.
It’s unclear whether this
plays a role in the 25% increase
in prevalence of alcohol problems noted
during the second postoperative year.
Even those who successfully
lose their excess weight
and keep it off appear to
have a hard time coping.
Ten years out, though physical health-
related quality-of-life improves,
general mental health tends
to significantly deteriorate
compared to pre-surgical levels
even among the biggest losers.
Ironically, there’s a common
notion that bariatric surgery
is for “cheaters” who
take the easy way out
by choosing the “low-effort”
method of weight loss.
Shedding the pounds may not shed
the stigma of even prior obesity.
Studies suggest that in the eyes
of others, knowing someone was fat
in the past leads them to always
be treated more like a fat person.
And there’s a strong anti-
surgery bias on top of that,
such that those who choose
the scalpel to lose weight
are rated most negatively
(for example, being considered
less physically attractive).
One can imagine how
remaining a target of prejudice
even after joining the
“in-group” could potentially
undercut psychological well-being.
There can also be unexpected
physical consequences of massive
weight loss like large hanging
flaps of excess skin.
Beyond being heavy and uncomfortable,
and interfering with movement,
the skin flaps can result
in itching, irritation,
dermatitis, and skin infections.
Getting a panniculectomy
(removing the abdominal “apron”
of hanging skin) can be expensive
and has a complication rate
exceeding 50%, with dehiscence
(rupturing of the surgical wound)
being the most common complication.
“Even if surgery proves
sustainably effective,”
wrote the founding director
of Yale University’s
Prevention Research Center, “the
need to rely on the rearrangement
of our natural gastrointestinal
anatomy as an alternative
to better use of feet and
forks [(diet and exercise)]
seems a societal travesty.”
In the Middle Ages, starving peasants
dreamed of gastronomic utopias
where food just rained
down from the sky.
The English called it
the Kingdom of Cockaigne.
Little could medieval fabulists predict
that many of their descendants
would not only take permanent
residence there, but cut out
parts of their stomachs and
intestines to combat the abundance.
Critics have pointed out the
irony of surgically altering
healthy organs to make them
dysfunctional—mal-absorptive—
on purpose, especially when
it comes to operating on children.
Bariatric surgery for kids and
teens has become widespread
and is being performed on children
as young as five years old.
Surgeons defend the practice
by arguing that growing up fat
can leave emotional scars and
“lifelong social retardation.”
Promoters of preventive medicine
argue that bariatric surgery
is the proverbial “ambulance
at the bottom of the cliff.”
In response, proponents of pediatric
bariatric surgery have written:
“It is often pointed out that
we should focus on prevention.
Of course, I agree. However,
if someone is drowning,
I don’t tell them, ‘You should learn
how to swim’; no, I rescue them.”
A strong case can be made that
the benefits of bariatric surgery
far outweigh the risks if the alternative
is remaining morbidly obese,
which is estimated to
shave up to a dozen
or more years off of one’s life.
Although there haven’t been any
data from randomized trials
to back it up yet, compared to
non-operated obese individuals,
those getting bariatric
surgery would be expected
to live significantly longer on average.
No wonder surgeons consistently
frame the elective surgery
as a life-or-death necessity.
This is a false dichotomy though.
The benefits only outweigh the risks
if there are no other alternatives.
Might there be a way to
lose weight healthfully
without resorting to the operating table?
That’s what my book
How Not to Diet is all about.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social media
to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts Podcast
landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics
you can order the e-book, audio book,
or hard copy of my latest book
“How to Survive a Pandemic.”
For recipes, check out my
“How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Which is my latest-latest book.
It’s beautifully designed, with more than 100
recipes for delicious and nutritious meals.
All the proceeds I receive from
the sales of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.